原视频名：How Amateur Radio Fans Decoded SpaceX's Telemetry & Engineering Video
原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/74_N163HyhA
原视频发布日期：20210315
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
Last weekend we saw two SpaceX launches carrying another two loads of Starlink satellites into space
上个周末 我们看到SpaceX进行了两次发射 将另外两批星链卫星送入太空
and one of those flew on a booster that was flying for its ninth time
其中一次发射使用了九手火箭
and was successfully recovered setting a new limit a new standard
并成功回收 定下了新的极限 新的标准
which is all very cool but I was more interested by the fact
这都是非常酷的 但我更感兴趣的事情是
that in Europe a bunch of amateur radio tinkers have managed to decode the telemetry
在欧洲 一群业余无线电爱好者已经成功地解码了遥测信号的数据
that is broadcast by the second stage in orbit including the footage from the engineering cameras.
也就是二级在轨发送的 包括工程相机的视频的数据
Now if you've watched a SpaceX broadcast you've probably seen footage from these very cameras.
那么如果你看过SpaceX的直播 你可能已经看到了这些相机拍下的视频
They have cameras pointing at the engines so they can check those work sometimes the satellite deployment.
他们的相机对准发动机 所以可以检查这些工作 有时还可以检查卫星的部署情况
And occasionally you might catch a glimpse of the camera inside the liquid oxygen tank
你可能还会偶尔瞥见液氧储罐内相机的镜头
showing the oxygen floating around in 0g as it sits in orbit.
显示出在没有负荷 火箭入轨的情况下 液氧正在漂浮
Now normally on the SpaceX broadcast they cut away for that stuff
那么通常在SpaceX的直播中 他们都会把这些镜头切换掉
but apparently the way this works is
但显然 这种(视频传输)的工作方式是
the cameras just cycle through what they're programmed to do on the ground
相机只是循环地完成它们在地面上编程好的工作
and the people producing the live stream they have to like switch away from the oxygen tanks.
而制作直播的人 必须切换掉液氧储罐的镜头
So yeah amateur radio tinkerers have figured out how to pull this apart.
那么是的 业余无线电爱好者已经搞清楚如何把视频从遥测数据中抽取出来
They use like one meter plus dishes which have to be very carefully tracked to point at the spacecraft
他们使用大概一米多的碟型天线 并将其非常小心地跟踪并指向航天器
as it passes over the horizon.
当二级火箭在地平线上通过时
Now SpaceX normally when they're doing their worldwide coverage,
那么通常情况下 在SpaceX做全球覆盖时
they have a number of base stations in different locations
他们会使用许多不同地方的基站
which they are using to receive the traffic as the thing passes overhead.
同时在二级通过基站上空时接收数据
and they have to plan this out ahead for every mission.
而在每次任务之前 就得提前计划好
But yeah this is being broadcast to everyone so if you've got a big enough dish you can do it.
但是 是的 数据也会发送给每个人 所以如果你的天线足够大 你就能做到这一点
Now that's getting radio signals down turning those radio signals into telemetry that can be decoded
那么 这些是负责把无线电信号传下来 之后则是把信号转变为可以解码的遥测数据
and something that can be understood is not a trivial thing by any means.
以及可以理解的东西 绝不是一件小事
So a lot of this is done.
那么很多事情都是这样做的
Well this is all done these days using something called software defined radio.
现在这些工作都是通过软件无线电来完成的
And as you can imagine this is where you use software to define your radio
你可以想象这是用软件来定义无线电的意思
because in the old days when radio first appeared
因为在以前无线电刚出现的时候
you would have to have a bunch of circuits that would take your input signal and modulate it
你必须要有一堆电路来接收你的输入信号 并对其进行调制
and perhaps you filter it and send that
也许你可以过滤一下 然后把它发出去
and then on the other end you would have to demodulate it and do all your filters.
然后在另一端 你将不得不解调它 同时再进行滤波
All these different components can now be implemented in software
所有这些不同的组件现在都可以在软件中实现
because computers are fast enough.
因为电脑的速度已经够快了
And a few years ago basically suddenly got very very cheap to build one of these software decoders
而在几年前 基本上 制作一个这样的软件解码器 突然变得非常非常便宜
because some hardware hackers realized that there was a digital TV dongle
因为一些硬件黑客意识到 有一个数字电视加密适配器
that you could buy for your PC that plugged it in via USB.
可以给你的电视购买 能插到USB上面
so you could watch your digital TV for those people that somehow hadn't heard of youtube.
这样就可以看数字电视了 对于那些没听说过油管的人来说
But these things had a software defined radio chip on them
但这些东西包含一个软件无线电芯片
and you could just change the software that was being run on those so that they could decode anything.
你可以只改变其上运行的软件 这样就可以解码任何东西
They could talk to or listen to GPS or all sorts of other stuff
可以与GPS或其他各种东西对话或监听
and essentially it's the same technique that's being used to talk to these satellites.
基本上也是用同样的技术与这些卫星对话
Now apparently the frequency range these are up in the S-band around 2.3 gigahertz.
那么显然这些频率范围是在S波段的2.3GHz左右
Apparently that's too high for these cheap software-defined radio things.
显然 这对这些廉价的软件无线电东西来说太高了
So there's another gizmo which I don't quite understand but apparently what it does is it just
所以还有一个我不太明白的小玩意 但显然它的作用是
it shifts the frequency down
将频率下移
so that you can use your your cheap software decoder to actually decode the whole thing.
这样你就可以用你的廉价软件解码器 来实际解码整个东西
Okay so that's one thing.
好了 这(只)是一件事
Now you're decoding it but just because you can see there's a signal there
现在你正在解码它 但只是因为你看到了一个信号
doesn't mean you can necessarily figure out what's going on with it
并不代表你一定能弄清楚其中的含义
and that requires a whole lot of understanding what's going on
而这需要大量的了解
and frankly I'm amazed at people that were able to look at this
而坦率地说 我很惊讶于那些能够留意到这个的人
and figure out how a bunch of radio noise turned into a bunch of bits.
同时弄清楚一堆无线电噪声是如何变成一堆比特的
And a lot of the work was apparently done in the sense that SpaceX followed known standards.
而很多工作显然是在SpaceX遵循已知标准的情况下完成的
There's something called the Consultative Committee for Space Data Systems, CCSDS.
有一个叫空间数据系统咨询委员会的东西 简称CCSDS
And they have a bunch of standards for good practices
他们有一堆可用于良好实践的标准
to basically say how you should build your telemetry system.
基本上说就是建立遥测系统的方法
So a lot of that stuff was already there
所以很多东西都已经存在了
and they just needed to figure out which options SpaceX had picked.
他们只需要弄清楚 SpaceX选择了哪些选项
It wasn't encrypted.
它没有加密
Although there is something called a scrambler or randomizer
虽然有一种叫扰频器或随机器的东西
which is like a standard thing when you're trying to do data dance communication
这就像一个标准的东西 当你试图进行数据交流（？）时
because the way radio works
因为无线电的工作方式
if you want to send a bit stream and you have like a whole bunch of zero bits
如果你想发送一个比特流 会产生一大堆零位
you don't want to send those as just zeros
你不会想把这些零位当零发送吧
because you actually need the signal to be going and alternating bits essentially.
因为你实际上需要信号持续地翻转比特
So that you still have reference transitions for your timers
所以 你需要为计时器准备参考性的转换器（？）
and so that you're not focusing too much of your radio energy on one part of your band-pass.
这样你不需要在带通(滤波器)上面花费太多的无线电能量
And letting the others sit around doing nothing.
而让其他部分无所事事
So this was a standard. This isn't an encryption system.
所以这是一个标准 这不是一个加密系统
This is just an encoding system that ensures that you get the most out of your radio spectrum. Let's say.
这只是一个编码系统 以确保充分利用了无线电频谱 可以这么说
But that was a standard one.
但这是一个标准的版本
Once they got that down and they got past the error correction. They had a bit stream.
一旦他们把这部分搞定 并完成错误校正 就得到了比特流
And I sort of understand decoding bit streams.
我对比特流的解码有一定的了解
In this case what they did was they aligned it to bytes and then just ran the Unix strings command.
在这种情况下 他们所做的是将其对齐为字节 然后运行Unix字符串命令
What that does is it just looks for ASCII text
来寻找ASCII编码的文本
and sure enough they found a bunch of bits where it had messages from GPS software
果然 他们发现了一些有GPS软件信息的数据
saying oh having trouble doing this or locking on.
内容是存在问题或者已锁定
These were just English human readable text messages
这些只是可读的英文文本信息
and I think this is debug logs from GPS subsystems.
我想这是GPS子系统的调试日志
But yeah, once you get through that you start to see that there are packets
但是 一旦到了这段信息的后面 你开始看到这种数据包
with header sizes and various structures on it.
带有头部大小的信息 以及各种结构
There's a bunch of different packet types. Only a few have been figured out.
有一堆不同的数据包类型 只有少数几种被弄明白了
But the most interesting one is of course the ones that contain video.
但最有趣的当然是那些包含视频的数据包
And these are just standard mpeg4 transport streams which is container format containing H.264 video
而这些只是标准的mpeg4传输流 也就是是包含H.264(编码)的视频的封装格式
and once you take all that you can turn that into video streams
一旦你把所有的数据收集起来 就可以把它变成视频流
and you can watch the stuff
同时进行观看
without the SpaceX producers switching you away when you really wanted to take a look at that oxygen tank
这样在看液氧储罐画面时 就不会被SpaceX直播的监制换掉画面了
so look this is obviously very cool.
那么这显然是很棒的
I'm not sure how long they'll be able to do this for.
我不知道他们能够这样做多久
It's entirely possible that SpaceX decides that they don't like people looking in this
完全有可能发生这样的事 也就是SpaceX决定不想让人们看到这个画面
It might be that they actually find there's some legal requirement for them to secure their streams a little more.
也可能是他们为数据流的加密找到了一些法律要求
But I'm not sure about that.
但是我对此并不确定
应该是指START I，NEW START似乎并没有相关要求
www.armscontrol.org/act/2010-05/new-start-good-news-us-security
I know actually there's apparently some of the missile treaties between the US and Russia
我知道其实在美国和俄罗斯之间的一些导弹条约当中 显然有一些
require that ICBM test telemetry not be encrypted
要求洲际弹道导弹试验遥测不加密
so that each country can spy and determine that the performance claims are being made are legit.
以便每个国家都能监视并确定其所宣称的性能是否合法
I don't think that necessarily applies to rockets in space.
我认为这不一定适用于太空中的火箭
It is also worth noting that one of the individuals involved in this
另外值得注意的是 参与此事的一个人
youtu.be/sknX7VxXQG8?t=594
also was responsible for getting data from the Chang'e 5 spacecraft and getting images from their engineering cameras
还负责从嫦娥五号航天器上获取数据 并从其工程相机上获取图像
so that again I'm surprised that one isn't encrypted
那么 这个信号也没有加密 也让我感到惊讶
but yeah look this is a whole fascinating field.
但是 是的 这个领域令人痴迷
I occasionally meet people that work in RF design and it blows my mind.
我偶尔会遇到在射频设计领域工作的人 而这让我大吃一惊
They have this whole language that I don't quite understand
他们的术语让我不太明白
but there's enough of it that I know that it fascinates me.
但足够让我着迷
So it'll be interesting to see how long we can keep doing this for interesting to see if we can see anything else.
所以 有趣的是我们还能这样看多久 以及看多少
What we've got and the most interesting thing we have I think is the images from inside the oxygen tank.
我认为 现在得到的 以及最有趣的东西是液氧储罐内部的图像
Because we do see sometimes in this case little blobs there people are saying they're bubbles.
因为我们有时会看到一些小的球状物 人们说那是气泡
No. These are spheres of liquid oxygen floating around in the tank.
不 这些是球状的液氧 在液氧储罐里漂浮着
But in another case we saw the liquid oxygen more or less stuck to the bottom of the tank via surface tension.
但在其他情况下 我们看到液氧通过表面张力部分地粘在罐底
So I think the different locations depend upon
所以我认为这里不同的位置取决于
what kind of maneuvers have been performed by the spacecraft before they light the engines.
火箭在点燃发动机之前进行了什么样的机动
They will of course use the reaction control thrusters to accelerate the booster forward
他们当然会使用反推力控制推进器(RCS)来加速二级火箭前进
so that oxygen ends and the fuel ends up on the bottom of the tanks.
这样 液氧和燃料最终都会沉到储罐的底部
But after you see an engine shut down stage two
但当你看到二级的那台发动机关闭后
that shutdown seems to be sufficiently violent that it knocks the propellant off the bottom
关机似乎足够猛烈 以至于它把推进剂推离了储罐底部
and then it starts floating around.
然后就开始四处飘动了
I would love to know more about this.
关于这方面 我想了解更多
I don't know why they're being so secret because I love it.
我不知道他们为什么要这么保密 因为我喜欢它
I think they should put lasers in the tank
我觉得他们应该在储罐里放上激光器
and create like a cool laser show with blobs of oxygen flowing around.
并在周围流动的液氧球中 创造出像酷炫的激光秀一样的效果
Spin the spacecraft. I don't know.
然后转动航天器 我不清楚
I'm just being a little silly now.
我只是傻了
Yeah so that that's some fascinating stuff that happened this weekend.
是的 所以这周末发生了一些迷人的事情
Mad props to the individuals who figured this out
非常感谢那些解码遥测数据的人
and I hope to see more from you.
我希望能看到更多来自你们的消息
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]